THIS STORY IS A WORK OF FICTION, AND NAMES OF CHARACTERS,
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
ORGANIZATIONS, AND OTHER OFFICIAL TITLES ARE ALL FICTIONAL CREATIONS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
Old man!
老爹！
I hope old man's doing well…
老爹不知道过得好不好
Oh, right. Yesterday, after the garden party….
对了 昨天游园会之后…
What are you saying?
你在说什么傻话？
The minister who ate the poison needed a lot of treatment!
吃了毒的大臣情况可是很严重呢
A patient should rest!
病人就好好躺着吧
Thanks to them, I slept well.
多亏了这样 睡得很饱
But I shouldn't have slept until noon.
不过睡到中午也睡太久了
I'd feel weird not wearing my freckles…
但现在要是不化妆…
You should've taken the day off today.
你今天休息也没关系的
That's not acceptable. If you need anything from me, just ask.
这怎么好意思 娘娘有什么事还请吩咐
Oh? Your freckles…
咦？你的雀斑…
I feel weird without them. Can I keep my face like this?
没有的话反而无法安心 还请允许我维持这个样子
Of course. You're right.
你说的有道理
Everyone rushed in demanding to know who my lady-in-waiting was.
大家都在追问“那个侍女是谁？”
It was hard!
很是辛苦呢
-I'm so sorry about that. -It's fine.
-真是非常抱歉 -没事
Oh, Gaoshun's been here since this morning. Do you want to talk to him?
比起那些 高顺早上就过来了 要怎么办呢？
He looked bored, so I asked him to weed the garden.
他看起来很无聊 所以我叫他去除草了
Weeding the garden…
除草…
He was seated in a high position at the garden party…
游园会的时候 明明坐在蛮高官的位置
He's such a diligent man…
真不愧是认真的男人
I'm sure that man is also
就算是那个男人
collecting his own group of lady-in-waiting fans.
一定也掳获了不少侍女的心吧
May we borrow the drawing room?
娘娘 可否借一个房间？
Certainly.
我知道了
-Hongniang? -Yes, my lady.
-红娘 -是
I feel like Hongniang's eyes are glistening too…
是错觉吗？ 总觉得红娘的眼睛也闪闪发光…
This is for you, from Sir Jinshi.
这是壬氏大人要交给你的
This is the soup that Lady Gyokuyou was meant to drink.
这是玉叶娘娘原本要喝的汤 对吧？
-Yes. -How thoughtful of you.
-是的 -真是慎重呢
-Don't eat it, all right? -I won't.
-请别喝下去 -我不会喝的
Silver corrodes quickly. The soup is oxidized.
银器很容易被腐蚀 汤已经氧化了
-It won't taste good. -It's about the taste…?
-已经不好吃了 -好吃吗…
Did you carry this with your bare hands?
您有直接用手拿过这个吗？
No. I didn't touch the bowl.
不 我没有碰到
I just dipped in a spoon to see if it was poison.
只有用汤匙舀起来 看看里面有没有毒物而已
After that, I wrapped it quickly with cloth.
然后就直接用布包起来了
Please wait a minute.
请稍待一下
Snip, snip, snip. Clatter, clatter, clatter.
喀嚓 哐当
-Cotton, powder, and a brush? -Yes.
-棉花、粉末和毛笔？ -没错
What will you do with these?
你要用这些做什么？
At the apothecary I worked at, to prevent pranks,
在我之前待的药局 为了防止恶作剧
we applied dye to containers you weren't supposed to touch.
我们会在不能碰的容器上涂上染料
I'm doing a version of that now.
现在要做一样的事情
It's easy. Add some powder to a rolled up cotton ball,
作法很简单 先将棉花揉成小球沾上粉末
and apply it on the container.
然后涂上容器
After that, I'll take off the extra powder using this brush.
最后再用毛笔将多余的粉末拨掉
-Here it is. -I see a white mark.
-出现了 -有白色的痕迹呢
This is the spot where someone touched the surface.
这就是人的手摸到的地方
Any spot touched by a fingertip leaves some sort of mark.
手指头摸过的地方会留下痕迹
This is especially true for silverware that corrodes easily.
容易被腐蚀的银器更是如此
Silverware is always wiped down with a cloth before being used.
因此银器在使用前 一定要用布擦过
In that case, the fingerprint left on this bowl now belongs to
也就是说 现在留着的指痕
the person who held this bowl after it was cleaned?
是在擦拭后才碰到碗的人
Exactly.
正是如此
The size and the location of the fingerprint
根据指痕的大小和位置
is enough to tell us how they held it.
就能够推测出拿餐具的方式
The person who held this bowl…
拿过这个碗的人…
What's wrong?
怎么回事？
It's nothing.
没什么
My guess is there were a total of four people that held this bowl.
恐怕拿过碗的总共有四人
Four people, you say?
你说四个人？
First are the three that touched around the bowl.
首先是碰过碗周围的三个人
The person who served the soup, the person who carried the bowl,
盛汤的人、配膳的人
the food taster for Lady Lishu,
还有里树娘娘的试毒人
and finally, one more. A third party who touched the rim of the bowl…
还有一个碰到碗边缘的“某人”
I think it's safe to assume that the poison was placed by this third party.
我想应该可以认定 下毒的就是这位“某人”
If that's true, why is the fingerprint
如果是这样
of the food taster found on a high-ranking concubine's bowl?
为何上级妃的碗会有试毒人的指痕？
It's simple.
很简单
The food taster for Lady Lishu swapped it on purpose to trouble her.
里树娘娘的试毒人 为了欺负她而故意调换食物
-Not knowing it was poison. -She swapped it?
-在不知情的情况下 -调换？
It's bullying.
这是一种欺凌
A lady-in-waiting bullying.
一介侍女
-To a high-ranking concubine? -So you don't believe it?
-欺凌上级妃？ -难以置信 对吧？
Please tell me.
可以说得详细点吗？
I want to warn you in advance that this is my personal speculation.
我得先说 这都不过是我的猜测而已
That's no problem.
没问题
Do you remember Lady Lishu's outfit at the garden party?
您对里树娘娘 在游园会的衣着有印象吗？
Yes. It was a flashy, pink costume.
有 我记得是华丽的深桃红色
Normally, if a concubine
一般而言
chooses an outfit that is too similar to Lady Gyokuyou's,
若娘娘选了和玉叶娘娘相似的衣服
the attendants would recommend a different outfit.
侍女应该会劝娘娘换上别的衣服
If not, the attendants would wear outfits that match their lady.
如果不是 那么侍女应该 会随着娘娘穿着相似的衣服
However, all her ladies-in-waiting were wearing white.
但里树娘娘的侍女 全都穿着白色的衣服
That made it seem as if Lady Lishu, who was wearing pink,
那样子让穿着深桃红色的里树娘娘
was a clown who couldn't read the room.
看起来就像是不识时务的丑角一样
Attendants are meant to support their lady.
侍女应该是要为主子着想的
If so, that day…
这样想来 那一天…
You can't even understand your own position as an attendant?
你们连侍女的立场 是什么都搞不清楚吗？
To think you recommended a pink outfit for her!
竟然让娘娘穿桃红色的衣服
Lady Ah-Duo's attendants were reprimanding
阿多娘娘的侍女
the incompetence of Lady Lishu's attendants.
是在训斥里树娘娘无能的侍女
In the rear palace,
在满是敌人的后宫
surrounded by enemies, the only people concubines can trust
妃子们能真心信赖的
are her own ladies-in-waiting.
只有自己的侍女
The young Lady Lishu merely followed the recommendation of her attendants
年轻的里树娘娘听从侍女们的建议
and wore that outfit
穿上了那件衣服
and was shamed publicly on purpose.
是刻意要让她出丑的
She had no idea.
她却毫无疑心
Not only that, but they also swapped meals
不仅如此 她们还调换了膳食
to trouble Lady Lishu even more?
想要更加为难里树妃？
Yes, without knowing it was poison. Though it ended up saving her life.
是的 但因为不知道下毒的事情 反倒是捡回了一条命
Their methods are dirty.
真是恶心的作法
Why would they do such a thing?
为什么她们要做这些事？
Lady Lishu is in the unique position of being the former emperor's concubine,
里树娘娘在年幼时 就成为了先帝的妃子
then entering monkhood soon after.
之后又马上出家 有着特殊的立场
She had been educated since childhood
她自幼受到的教养
that a wife serves her husband.
是妻子应当为丈夫鞠躬尽瘁
People must think that it is extremely immoral of her
从旁人来看 嫁给亡夫的儿子
to marry her late husband's son.
也太过不道德了
I think the print left on the rim
碗边缘的痕迹
belongs to the culprit who added the poison.
我想就是下毒的犯人留下的
-She held the rim to mix in the poison. -I see.
-应该是沿着边缘混入的 -原来如此
You must not dirty the area where a high-class person's lips touch
高贵的人嘴巴会碰到的地方
with your fingers.
不能用手指弄脏
Hongniang taught me that.
红娘是这样教我的
Those are my speculations.
我的见解就是这些了
-Can I ask you one thing? -What is it?
-我能问一件事吗？ -什么事？
Why did you try to cover for the food taster attendant yesterday?
你为什么要包庇 昨天那个试毒的侍女？
I'm just curious. I won't pursue this any further.
我只是好奇 没有别的意思
The life of an attendant
侍女的性命
is worth much less than that of a concubine.
和妃子比起来一点也不重要
Especially the life of a food taster…
更别说是试毒人的命了
I'll think of a good excuse for Sir Jinshi.
我会向壬氏大人好好说明
Thank you very much.
谢谢
I have to thank her in some way
毕竟特地调换了膳食
for swapping the bowls.
不道个谢不行呢
I did get to taste the poison, after all.
多亏了她才能尝到毒
I really should've swallowed that soup…
果然要是有把汤喝掉就好了
-That's all. -I see.
-事情就是这样 -我明白了
You're clever at wording things, as usual.
每次听都觉得你好会说话啊
-Is that so? -It's clearly an inside job, right?
-是这样吗？ -怎么想都是内贼吧？
Yes, looking at the circumstances.
现况看起来是这样
You put it so simply.
讲得倒简单
Because of this, I haven't slept since yesterday. I haven't even changed.
因为这个骚动 从昨天开始就没睡 连衣服都没换
I want to stop thinking.
我都想放弃思考了
Your true nature is coming out.
本性跑出来了哦
-No one's here. It's fine. -I'm here.
-又没人在 有差吗？ -有我在呢
-That doesn't count. -Yes sir, it does.
-你不算数 -不行
-There's no way to trick you, is there? -I've known you too long for that.
-说什么都没用呢 -毕竟服侍您这么久了
It's troublesome to be taken care of by someone since you were born…
打从出生就被 同一个人照顾着 还真是麻烦啊
Sir Jinshi. Your hair clip is still in your hair.
壬氏大人 发簪还插着呢
Oh, shit. I totally forgot.
不好 我忘得一乾二净了
It was hidden in your hair.
头发遮住了
I don't think anyone figured out your true status.
我想应该没有人察觉您真正的身分
Keep this, will you?
交给你保管了
Don't treat it so roughly.
又当成杂物乱丢
This can only be worn by those with special status. Be careful.
这可是特别身分的人才能穿戴的东西 请好好珍惜
-I know, I know. -No, you don't.
-我明白 -您不明白
All right, then. I'll be off.
那么我先告辞了
Time for work…
工作吧…
-So, did you receive any hair clips? -Yeah.
-所以你有收到发簪吗？ -算有吧
I see. That means…
是哦 那么…
You can leave the rear palace!
你可以离开后宫了！
-What did you say? -You can leave the rear palace?
-你刚刚说什么？ -你可以离开后宫了？
Give me the details!
把这件事详细告诉我
Yes, ma'am…
遵命…
In the rear palace, you can't meet men from the outside,
在后宫虽然见不到外面的男性
but with special permission, men could take palace women outside.
但要是有特别的许可 男性就能将宫女带出去
I see.
嗯
So that's what the hair clips being given out in the garden party mean.
许可就是游园会发的那些发簪吧
Exactly!
没错！
Alternately, you can use hair clips to ask to be let out of the rear palace.
相反地 如果你使用发簪的话 就可以请求从后宫出去
I see. Thanks, Xiaolan. I'll give it a try.
原来是这样 谢谢你小兰 我试试看
You're very welcome!
不客气
Maomao, thanks for the hawthorn fruit!
猫猫 多谢你的糖葫芦
It was delicious!
很好吃！
I've received four hair clips in total. Out of those, two were from men.
我一共收到四支发簪 其中有两支是男人送的
Wait. If they lost their "male parts," are they not called men…?
等等 失去了重要的部位 还能称作男人吗？
Apothecary!
药师！
Okay.
好吧
Sir Lihaku, a palace woman from the rear palace is here.
李白大人 有一位后宫的宫女送来了这个
What? All right.
什么？我知道了
What should I do? An obligatory hair clip was taken seriously…
糟糕了 她把做做样子的发簪当真了吗？
But I'd hate to turn down a beauty's invitation…
但如果是个美女 拒绝就太可惜了
I only gave a clip to one attendant from the Jade Pavilion.
翡翠宫的侍女我应该只有给一位
That means…
也就是说…
It's her!
是她啊！
So, how should I refuse her?
那么要如何拒绝她呢？
Excuse me.
打扰了
Sorry for the wait.
让您久等了
Wait, who are you?
嗯？你是谁啊？
-I hear that a lot. -Makeup really changes your looks.
-常有人这么说 -有人说你化妆后判若两人吗？
I hear that a lot too.
那个也常有人说
And to call on me, of all people?
但你又把我叫出来 代表…
I'd like to visit home.
我想回老家一趟
Home? Do you even know what this means?
老家？你知道这是什么意思吗？
I hear that it's possible to visit home temporarily
我听说只要您能为我担保
if you can be my guarantor.
我就能够暂时返家
You've got some nerve.
你还真是放肆
An attendant like you, asking a soldier like me to be a guarantor?
竟敢用侍女的身分 要求身为武官的我替你做担保？
Exactly.
没错
And you called me all the way here just for that?
你特地把我叫出来就为了这件事？
Shall I call you bold or reckless?
该说你大胆 还是不要命了？
So what?
所以呢？
You're asking me to be used as a tool so you can visit home?
你是想要利用我 好让你可以返家？
Not at all. I have something in mind to gift you for the favor.
不尽然 小女子也准备了相应的谢礼
THE VERDIGRIS HOUSE REFERRAL: MEIMEI
（绿青馆介绍状 梅梅）
How about a flower-watching party at the Verdigris House?
到绿青馆赏个花如何？
The Verdigris House?
绿青馆？
You're joking! That brothel is worth a year's salary!
你说笑吧！那可是一个晚上 就要花掉一年薪俸的高级青楼啊！
No need to worry. You'll understand once you see this referral.
担心的话 您看过介绍状就会明白了
Pairin. Joka. Meimei.
白铃、女华、梅梅
I can't believe this even more now!
越来越不敢相信了
Even high-ranking officials can barely afford those Three Princesses!
这不是即使是高官 也无法轻易出手的“三美人”吗？
If you can't believe me, it can't be helped.
您不相信的话也无可奈何
I'm sorry for taking your time.
非常抱歉 浪费了您的时间
-Wait… -This is extremely unfortunate.
-等等 -真是非常遗憾
I'll ask elsewhere. Please pretend I never asked…
我只好另请高明了 这件事就请您当作没发生过吧
Does this woman have other offers?
这女人还有其他的吗？
And they're rose quartz and silver hair clips?
而且还是红水晶和银制的发簪？
They're both of higher statuses than me!
这些官位显然比我还要高！
Who is this girl?
这小姑娘究竟是何方神圣？
Does this mean that this offer is legitimate…?
这样的话 这件事说不定可行？
No, it's too suspicious!
不 实在太可疑了！
But if it's really true, I'd never have the chance to meet
但如果是真的话 见到三美人的机会
the Three Princesses again…
恐怕仅此一次
What should I do?
我该怎么做才好？
So, what will you do?
您意下如何？
I accept my loss.
我认输了
Congrats, Maomao!
恭喜你 猫猫！
To think that Maomao would beat us…
没想到猫猫竟然比我们快
-I'm so glad! -You must've met someone wonderful!
-太好了 -你遇到了好人呢
Thank you.
谢谢
Why are you so carefree?
你为什么能这么平淡？
It's okay. I'll bring back souvenirs.
别担心 我会带土产回来的
-How did you meet this man? -I just went with the flow…
-你是怎么遇到他的？ -顺其自然地…
From the looks of it, she doesn't know the meaning of hair clips at all.
看那样子 她绝对不知道发簪的意思吧？
Yes. I'm certain.
是啊 一定不知道
Geez. I feel the worst for him…
真是的 那孩子太可怜了
This is so fun.
真好玩
What face would he make?
那孩子会是什么样的表情呢？
Oh, gosh. Looks like there's going to be another drama…
真是的 感觉又会引起一场纷争了
Jinshi, having finished his work,
当壬氏处理完公务
got bored and came to visit
好不容易有闲造访时
the day after Maomao's departure.
已经是猫猫出发后的隔天了
Maomao left with some mysterious man…
要找猫猫的话 她跟着某个人一起离开了哦
To visit home for three days!
她回家三天
My home, the pleasure district, is not so far away.
老家所在的花街并不是非常远的地方
After crossing the fence and moat of the rear palace,
从后宫出发 越过城墙和护城河后
it's within walking distance.
就是走路可以到达的距离
How extravagant, riding a carriage for this distance…
竟然坐马车 真是太奢侈了
But the Three Princesses at the Verdigris House
不过说到绿青馆的三美人
are almost a god-like idol admired even by regular people, after all…
是连平民们都向往的云上偶像
It's an honor to be able to witness them even once.
只要能见上一面 就能倍感光荣的存在
We're almost there!
哦 看得到了
It's the pleasure district!
是花街
There are girls that come to the district wanting to become like their idols,
虽然也有向往成为那样的存在 而前来花街的女孩
but it's not so easy.
但并不是那么简单就能当上的
Even for apprentices, or courtesans-in-training,
这是即使是见习娼妓小丫头
there's no guarantee she'd sell.
也不能保证能卖得好的世界
-So this is the Verdigris House… -Yes.
-这儿就是绿青馆… -没错
VERDIGRIS HOUSE
（绿青馆）
It's very dignified.
感觉有种气势呢
It's a historical brothel with a full lineup from middle-ranking to
因为这是聚集了中等到最上等的娼妓
the highest ranking courtesan.
老字号的青楼啊
Long time no see, Granny!
好久不见了 婆婆
How's everyone doing…
大家都还…
What do you mean, "Long time no see"?
什么“好久不见”？
You idiot!
你这笨丫头！
Are you okay? What's wrong with this old woman?
你没事吧？那老太婆是怎么回事？
That's Grams, the owner of the Verdigris House.
那是老鸨 是绿青馆的馆主
Brings me back.
真怀念啊
This is how I used to vomit poison back in the day.
以前她总是这样让我把毒吐出来
What? So this is the very rich patron?
什么啊？这就是你说的贵客吗？
He has a handsome face, and a good body too.
长得挺有男性魅力 体格也不错
I hear you got promoted young.
听说你也是年轻有为啊
Granny, that's not something to say to someone's face.
婆婆 这不该当着本人的面讲吧？
Hey, go get Pairin.
喂 去叫白铃
-She should be taking tea today. -Yes!
-她今天应该在磨茶才是 -是
-Pairin… -Are you confident in your arm muscles?
-白铃… -李白大人对手臂的肌肉有自信吗？
I do train daily.
我可是有好好锻炼身体的
Oh? Maybe this could work…
这肌肉量…说不定…
Right this way!
请跟我来
I'm nervous.
好紧张啊
-Good luck out there! -Thanks!
-好好表现哦 -好！
Maomao. I can't deal with you.
猫猫 你真是的
Disappearing for ten months without contacting us…
十个月以来 一声联络都没有就消失了
I had no other choice. You didn't read the wood tablet I sent?
我也没办法 你没看我送来的木简吗？
Of course I did! Why else would I entertain a first-timer?
我当然看了 否则怎么会 给第一次来的人这等招待？
I know.
我知道啦
This is half of all I earned at the rear palace so far.
这是在后宫工作至今一半的薪俸
I asked them to pay in advance.
我特地请他们先预支给我
This is Pairin we're talking about!
接客的可是白铃啊
This isn't enough at all.
才这么点根本不够
-Come on. It's just tea! -Idiot!
-就喝个茶而已 可以吧？ -蠢蛋！
You don't really think nothing's happening with those arms?
看看那手臂 白铃不可能什么都不做吧？
You think?
果然吗？
-But that's out of my control… -Of course not!
-但那是不可抗力… -说什么傻话
I'll add it to your receipt.
我会好好算在帐上的
I can't pay…
我付不起啊…
Then give me all your best customers!
那就再多找点贵客过来啊
Like that one, someone young who I can keep squeezing out of!
像刚刚那种年轻 又能够适度被压榨的家伙
Could a eunuch be a customer?
宦官也算是客人吗？
Not him. The courtesans would fall head over heels and run out of business.
那家伙可不行 娼妓们认真起来的话 可是会把店搞垮的
I'd feel bad about offering Gaoshun or the quack doctor…
但要找高顺还是庸医 都觉得不对啊…
Maomao. Old man should be at home. Go to him.
猫猫 老爹应该在家 快去找他吧
Just crossing a street from the pleasure district
仅仅穿过一条街
changes the scenery completely.
花街的景色就会变了个模样
The dilapidated houses, beggars, and the syphilitic streetwalkers.
排列整齐的房屋 到处充满了乞丐、梅毒患者和流莺
It hasn't changed at all.
一点都没变呢
I'm home, old man.
我回来了 老爹
Oh, welcome home. You're late.
噢 欢迎回家 真晚呢
I finally arrived home.
我终于回家了
I was out getting dye for my freckles that day.
其实那天 我是去采雀斑要用的染料
But then…
结果…
I still have my term of service.
因为期限还没到
-I'm going back in two days. -I see.
-后天我就要回后宫了 -这样啊
I'm sleepy, but I want a bath.
虽然很困 但真想洗个澡啊
Go borrow the bath at the Verdigris House tomorrow.
明天再去绿青馆借澡堂吧
I'll do that.
就这么办
The rear palace, huh?
后宫啊…
Some trick of fate, huh?
这就是因果吧
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next episode, "Wheat Stalks".
下一集 《麦秆》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易